Today's דף daf is פ״ג Pe Gimmel 83, and we pick up
at the top of פ״ג עמוד א׳, Pe Gimmel Amud Aleph, נכנס
לפנים. Nichnas Lifnim. We are
finishing up the discussion
of how when the blood of a חטאת, Chatas, and according to
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva other קרבנות, Korbanos, is brought to the inside
into the היכל Heichal and the קודש הקדשים Kodesh HaKodashim that it
invalidates.
And then the גמרא Gemara ended with an interesting discussion about what
if it
isn't an inner חטאת Chatas but the blood got brought all the
way into the קודש הקדשים? Kodesh HaKodashim? You know, what if it
was the חטאת Chatas of יום כיפור Yom Kippur and it went
into the קודש הקדשים, Kodesh HaKodashim, came out and went back in?
Anyway, but that's the basic sort of focus. And now we deal
with the question because the פסוק Pasuk says, וכל חטאת אשר יובא
מדמה לכפר בקודש
אל הקודש פנימה. V'chol chatas asher yuva midamah l'chapper bakodesh el hakodesh
penimah. So it's being brought in for the purpose of atonement. So
there's a debate of תנאים: Tannaim: Does that mean the intent, or
does that mean it actually was used in a ritual of atonement,
which you need in order to invalidate the חטאת? Chatas? So תניא,
Tanya, we learn in a בריתא, Braisa, רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says,
it says here לכפר בקודש, L'chapper bakodesh, and it says להלן, lehalan,
וכל אדם לא יהיה באהל מועד בבואו לכפר בקודש. V'chol adam lo
yihyeh b'Ohel Moed b'vo-o l'chapper bakodesh. It says by the כהן גדול,
Kohen Gadol, nobody should be in the אהל מועד Ohel Moed when
he enters for the sake of atonement, לכפר בקודש. L'chapper bakodesh. So
מה להלן בשלא כיפר, Mah lehalan beshelo kipper, there obviously it doesn't
mean when he is doing the atonement; the whole point is that
people have to clear out when he enters in. So it's the
point of he's entering for that purpose, but even without having done
the act.
There's going to be people there
when, whether you're emptying out or making sure you're not there. אף
כאן בשלא כיפר. Af kan beshelo kipper. So here too, when it
says you bring the blood in לכפר, L'chapper, it means that's the
purpose; it doesn't mean that you actually did it. So that's a
reasonable read. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says no, he's going to make
another link. נאמר כאן לכפר, Ne'emar kan l'chapper, and it says להלן,
lehalan, ואת פר החטאת ואת שעיר החטאת אשר הובא את דמם לכפר
בקודש. V'es par hachatas v'es se'ir hachatas asher huva es damam l'chapper
bakodesh. Again, a פסוק Pasuk by יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, but here
it's speaking about the past, not the future. It says the ox
of the חטאת Chatas and the goat of the חטאת Chatas that
their blood was brought in to atone, לכפר בקודש. L'chapper bakodesh. But
it doesn't just mean that was the intent why their blood was
brought in; it means it was brought in to atone and it
actually was used in the atonement process. And you know because you
would not be doing the next ritual here of burning them had
the blood not actually been done properly. So obviously here לכפר L'chapper
means it was done for that purpose and that was what was
actually done to them. מה להלן כשכיפר אף כאן כשכיפר. Mah lehalan
keshekipper af kan keshekipper. Okay, so each one quotes from a different
פסוק Pasuk by יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, whether לכפר בקודש L'chapper bakodesh
is prospective,
meaning is it looking forward towards what's going to be but it
hasn't been done yet, or is it retrospective? Okay, so the גמרא
Gemara says, במאי קמיפלגי? Bemai kamiflagi? Which determines which פסוק Pasuk you
learn it from? So מר סבר, Mar savar, דנים חוץ מחוץ. Danim
chutz michutz. You learn out things that are supposed to be on
the outside from something supposed to be on the outside. Meaning, the
blood of an outer חטאת Chatas is supposed to be on the
outside. So it says if its blood is brought in לכפר בקודש,
L'chapper bakodesh, but
it's basically stepping over a boundary by being brought in. So similarly
when it speaks by יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, it says no person
should be in the אהל מועד Ohel Moed when the כהן גדול
Kohen Gadol goes לכפר בקודש. L'chapper bakodesh. So it's talking about sort
of remaining on the outside and not traversing that boundary. Okay, so
that's why those two are seen as similar. It's about whether you
belong on the outside or belong on the inside. So therefore we're
going to link those לכפרs l'chapper and say the לכפר l'chapper is
the intent in which it's being brought in. ומר סבר, UMar savar,
דנים בהמה מבהמה. Danim behemah mibehemah. No, no, no, because we're going
to focus on whether the verse refers to the animal or the
blood. So when it speaks about any חטאת Chatas whose blood is
brought in לכפר בקודש, L'chapper bakodesh, we're describing the blood. The blood
being brought in לכפר בקודש. L'chapper bakodesh. When we talk about the
קרבנות Korbanos on יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, it says את פר החטאת
ואת שעיר החטאת אשר הובא את דמם לכפר בקודש. Es par hachatas
v'es se'ir hachatas asher huva es damam l'chapper bakodesh. Their blood was
brought in. So in those two cases, the words לכפר בקודש L'chapper
bakodesh are describing the בהמה, Behemah, or more specifically are describing the
blood. And therefore we're going to link those. And since in one
case it means that's how the blood was actually used, in this
case it also means that's how the blood was actually used. ואין
דנים בהמה מאדם. V'ein danim behemah me'adam. And we don't focus on,
we don't connect it to a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol where it
talks about why is he going in. It's not a question about
why the person is going in. The כהן גדול Kohen Gadol is
going in to in the future be לכפר בקודש. L'chapper bakodesh. It's
describing the blood. So blood לכפר בקודש L'chapper bakodesh means blood that
was already used for that purpose. Okay, so that's the question: What
makes an outer חטאת Chatas invalid when the blood is brought in?
Is it sufficient that it's brought in for the intent of being
used for ritual, or does it actually have to be used for
that ritual?
Last opinion in the משנה: Mishnah: רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehudah says that
it's only if it's done intentionally. Presumably he reads לכפר, L'chapper, that
you're doing it willingly and not בשוגג. B'shogeg. So the question is:
What does he mean by בשוגג? B'shogeg? Like does בשוגג... B'shogeg... Like
does בשוגג b'shogeg mean if it means that you didn't realize you
were carrying blood or whatever, then presumably everybody agrees to that too
because it wasn't brought in for the sake of לכפר בקודש. l'chaper
bakodesh. So the best I can figure is that he means that
you didn't realize it was outer חטאת Chatas blood, you thought it
was inner חטאת Chatas blood. So then it's not clear which פסוק
pasuk he's getting that from but anyway that's what he says. He
says it's only if it's intentional not if it's שוגג. shogeg. So
the גמרא Gemara says המזיד פסול. Hamayzi pasul. Okay, but at least
obviously he would agree that intentionally it is invalid. So now it
wants to figure out how does he hold in terms of the
previous debate, because his point about שוגג shogeg and מזיד mayzid is
not directly connected to the earlier discussion of the definition of לכפר
בקודש. l'chaper bakodesh. So it says, המזיד פסול, Hamayzi pasul, בשעת כיפר
או בלא כיפר? bish'as kiper o b'lo kiper? Do you actually have
to sprinkle the blood or not? How does he hold about the
previous debate? So אמר רבי ירמיה, amar Rebbi Yermia, ממשמע
שנאמר, mimashma shene'emar, ואת פר החטאת, v'eis par hachattas, he's going to
quote a ברייתא braisa and from this ברייתא braisa we're going to
see a position of רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda that is going to
teach us, from which we will figure out how רבי יהודה Rebbi
Yehuda holds in the previous debate, whether the blood was intended to
be used or actually used. Okay, so here's the ברייתא. braisa. ממשמע
שנאמר
ואת פר החטאת ואת שעיר החטאת אשר הובא
דמם, mimashma shene'emar v'eis par hachattas v'eis se'ir hachattas asher huvas damam,
so if once it says the פר החטאת par hachattas that their
blood was brought, this is going back to יום כיפור, Yom Kippur,
לכפר בקודש מה תלמוד לומר? l'chaper bakodesh mah talmud lomar? Sorry,
אשר הובא דמם לכפר בקודש. asher huvas damam l'chaper bakodesh. It says
their blood was brought to atone, that you burn them, this is
the חטאת chattas of יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. מה תלמוד לומר והשורף?
mah talmud lomar v'hasoreif? What's the point of the end of the
verse? The end of the verse there by יום כיפור Yom Kippur
says that the one who burns them, he and his garments are
טמא. tamei. So the גמרא Gemara says, what do you mean מה
תלמוד לומר והשורף? mah talmud lomar v'hasoreif? לגופיה איצטריך. l'gufei itzrich. What
do you mean what do you need that פסוק pasuk for? You
need it for exactly what it's saying, to teach you the הלכה
halacha that the person who burns these animals becomes טמא. tamei. So
no,
אלא מה תלמוד לומר חטאת חטאת? ela mah talmud lomar chattas chattas?
Why does it say ואת פר החטאת ואת שעיר החטאת? v'eis par
hachattas v'eis se'ir hachattas? Why doesn't it say ואת הפר ואת השעיר
אשר הובא דמם? v'es hapar v'hase'ir asher huvas damam? We know they're
sin offerings, right? Why does the תורה Torah when describing these sin
offerings that are burnt on יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, why does it
repeat the word חטאת? chattas? לפי שלא למדנו אלא לפר ושעיר של
יום הכיפורים שנשרפים בבית הדשן ומטמא בגדים l'fi shelo lamadnu ela l'par
v'se'ir shel Yom Hakipurim shenisrafim b'veis hadeshen um'tamei begadim because we only
know this is true by
the inner חטאות chattaos that they're burnt בבית הדשן, b'veis hadeshen, which
means they're burnt outside the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash.
Actually רש"י Rashi points out we know that about the other inner
חטאות chattaos as well, but the key line is the punchline at
the end. We only know the inner חטאת chattas when you burn
them outside the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash causes a person and his
clothes to become טמא. tamei. Okay, we only know this הלכה, halacha,
the end פסוק pasuk והשורף אותם, v'hasoreif osam, the פסוק pasuk only
says that by the inner
חטאת chattas of יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, the שעיר se'ir and the
פר par of יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. How do we know this
about the other inner חטאות, chattaos, like the פר העלם דבר, par
helem davar, the thing that we talked about for you know by
הוריות, Horayos, or שעיר עבודה זרה, se'ir avodah zarah, you know,
so how do we know that those two are burnt outside? So
the גמרא Gemara says,
שנשרפים בבית הדשן ומטמא בגדים שאר נשרפים מנין? shenisrafim b'veis hadeshen m'tamei
begadim shear nisrafim minayin? How do we know other ones? Meaning other
inner חטאות. chattaos. How do we know that they
also? Wait a minute. He says, תלמוד לומר חטאת חטאת דברי רבי
יהודה. talmud lomar chattas chattas divrei Rebbi Yehuda. So רבי יהודה Rebbi
Yehuda says that the extra, that's why we say ואת פר החטאת
ואת שעיר החטאת v'eis par hachattas v'eis se'ir hachattas to extend it
to all types of חטאות, chattaos, not just the, all whatever, all
inner חטאות, chattaos, okay, fine, that's what you do with it. So
that's how you know it applies to other inner חטאות chattaos that
you burn that the person becomes טמא. tamei. So רבי מאיר אומר,
Rebbi Meir omer, to which רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir responds,
אינו צריך. eino tzarich. I don't need to use the word חטאת
chattas to tell me that. הרי הוא אומר, harei hu omer, the
verse explains the character of these קרבנות korbanos that have this הלכה.
halacha. And the verse says, ואת פר החטאת ואת שעיר החטאת שאין
תלמוד לומר לכפר. v'eis par hachattas v'eis se'ir hachattas she'ein talmud lomar
l'chaper. Why does it have to say that they were brought to
atone? We know what they were brought to. It's describing the חטאות
chattaos of יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. מה תלמוד לומר לכפר? mah talmud
lomar l'chaper? Why does it describe them and say these were brought
inside to atone? אם כל המתכפרים שהשורפן מטמא בגדים im kol hamiscaprim
sheharsorfam m'tamei begadim to tell you the הלכה halacha we're about to
say, והשורף אותם יכבס בגדיו, v'hasoreif osam yichabes begadav, that if you
burn them you become טמא. tamei. That הלכה halacha is not unique
to these two חטאות. chattaos. What's distinctive or what makes these חטאות
chattaos special is אשר הובא דמם לכפר בקודש, asher huvas damam l'chaper
bakodesh, that the blood was brought in the inner, you know, in
the inside to do like in the היכל Heichal and the היכל.
Heichal. So therefore from there I can learn that any inner חטאת
chattas the same הלכה halacha would apply because it's saying the important
characteristic here is אשר הובא דמם לכפר. asher huvas damam l'chaper. So
they both agree on the הלכה. halacha. This הלכה halacha that if
when you burn the inner חטאות chattaos the person and the clothes
become טמא, tamei, they both agree that it applies to all inner
חטאות. chattaos. רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda learns it from the repetition of
the word חטאת חטאת chattas chattas and רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir learns
it from the fact that they're described and characterized as אשר הובא
דמם לכפר בקודש, asher huvas damam l'chaper bakodesh, which means that any
animal that's in that category the same הלכה halacha would apply.
Fine. The blood isn't brought on the inside.
Yes, but we're not saying any חטאת, chatat, we're saying only an
inner חטאת. chatat. Okay, right. And so only an inner חטאת chatat
or another way of saying this is only blood that was brought
inside לכפר בקודש. l'chaper bakodesh. So now the גמרא Gemara just says
so that actually רבי מאיר'ס Rabbi Meir's דרשה drasha seems a more
straightforward one rather than learn it from an extra word, we're actually
learning it from the explicit description of the verse. So why would
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda go to these extra words חטאת חטאת chatat
chatat and not learn it from the explicit description of the verse?
So the גמרא Gemara says רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda so לכפר l'chaper
לא משמע ליה. lo mashma leh. מאי טעמא, Mai ta'ama, why not
learn it from לכפר l'chaper that's such an explicit description, from there
you can learn the הלכה? halacha? לאו משום דמיבעי ליה לגזירה שוה?
Lav mishum d'mibai leh l'gzeira shava? It must be he uses לכפר
בקודש l'chaper bakodesh to teach you something else. What does he use
לכפר בקודש l'chaper bakodesh to teach you? It must be he links
that to the לכפר בקודש l'chaper bakodesh that we're dealing with about
what makes an outer חטאת chatat invalid when it's brought inside לכפר
בקודש. l'chaper bakodesh. So since, right, רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir isn't using
the words לכפר בקודש l'chaper bakodesh to tell you this הלכה halacha
of טומאה tumah and that it applies to all inner חטאות, chatatot,
he must be using it for something else. What else is he
using it for? To link it to an outer חטאת chatat whose
blood was brought inside לכפר בקודש. l'chaper bakodesh. And therefore, that teaches
you that for him it would not be enough that it would
be brought inside for that purpose, it actually would have to be
used, because the לכפר בקודש l'chaper bakodesh of ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah
יום... I'm mixing ראש השנה יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, I don't know
what's going on with me... of יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, here I
see I'm losing people,
okay. ביום כיפור By Yom Kippur it says, okay, וכל אדם לא
יהיה באהל מועד
בבואו לכפר בקודש,
v'chol adam lo yihyeh b'ohel moed b'vo'o
l'chaper
bakodesh, that's one thing it says. And another פסוק pasuk says ואת
פר החטאת ואת שעיר החטאת אשר הובא את
דמם
לכפר
בקודש. v'et par hachatat v'et se'ir hachatat asher huva et damam l'chaper
bakodesh. Okay, so this tells you, this tells you intent,
but you haven't done it yet, and this tells you
you've actually done it.
And what we want to know is, what the debate of the
תנאים Tannaim is, when it says by the outer חטאת chatat that
blood was brought on the inside, right,
when it says, when it says what's the פסוק? pasuk? וכל חטאת
אשר יובא מדמה אל אהל מועד לכפר בקודש באש תשרף. v'chol chatat
asher yuva midamah el ohel moed l'chaper bakodesh ba'esh tisaref. לא תאכל,
lo teachal, fine. לא תאכל, lo teachal, באש תשרף. ba'esh tisaref.
It said אל הקודש פנימה, el hakodesh penimah, is that a different
פסוק?
pasuk? We used that before too also.
Okay, so which one
is this לכפר
בקודש?
l'chaper
bakodesh? Is it intent,
or
is
it you actually did it? Okay, that was the debate of the
תנאים, Tannaim, which one to link it to. So now what we're
saying is רבי יהודה...
Rabbi Yehuda... והנה לא הובא את דמה אל הקודש פנימה אכל תאכלו
אותה. v'hineh lo huva et damah el hakodesh penimah achol tochelu otah.
Ah, that was by משה Moshe and אהרן, Aharon, אל הקודש פנימה.
el hakodesh penimah. Okay, that's a different פסוק. pasuk. That's another... but
that's the same הלכה halacha that you burn it. But that was
קודש פנימה, kodesh penimah, that was a discussion we had yesterday about
אהל מועד ohel moed or the... whether it was the היכל heichal
or... you know, how we know it's both the היכל heichal and
the קודש קדשים. kodesh kodashim. Anyway, this is the debate of תנאים.
Tannaim. Is it about intent or is it that you actually did
it? Then we have רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda who says a different
point: it's only במזיד b'meizid not בשוגג. b'shogeg. So we want to
know, which one does he hold about this: intent or you actually
did it? So we said, well, he learns the idea that this
הלכה halacha of טומאת בגדים, tumat begadim, right, then it says
והשורף אותם יכבס בגדיו. v'hasoref otam yechabes begadav. So this הלכה halacha
of טומאת בגדים, tumat begadim, he says we all agree applies not
just to the animals, the חטאות chatatot of יום כיפור, Yom Kippur,
but also any inner חטאת. chatat. So רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda gets
it from the words חטאת חטאת chatat chatat that it applies to
any inner חטאת. chatat. רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir gets it from the
words לכפר בקודש l'chaper bakodesh that we know that it applies to
any inner חטאת. chatat. So the גמרא Gemara says, why does רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda not learn it from the words לכפר בקודש? l'chaper
bakodesh? It must mean he needs these words to tell me a
different הלכה. halacha. What different הלכה halacha does he need it to
tell me? To link it to this case, and to tell me
that our case of an outer חטאת chatat whose blood is brought
inside, only invalidates when it's actually done. This לכפר בקודש l'chaper bakodesh
links to this, and only when you actually use the blood on
the inside, not when you just brought it with the intent. And
since that's what רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda does with לכפר בקודש l'chaper
bakodesh to learn the הלכה halacha that it causes טומאה tumah for
any inner חטאת, chatat, he has to learn from the extra words
חטאת חטאת. chatat chatat. Okay?
certain sins
cause impurity to the מקדש *Mikdash*? Something like that? Is that what?
Well,
that's a general יום כיפור *Yom Kippur* idea, but yes. But yeah,
that's not sort of being dealt with here. Okay. So now the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this. Okay.
The כפרה *kapara* here is refers to...
Well, right, I mean does the כפרה *kapara* mean to cleanse the
קודש *Kodesh* or does it mean... Right, it doesn't mean that you're
doing מכפר *mechaper* in the קודש *Kodesh*? I mean the פשט *pshat*
of the פסוק pasuk, *pasuk* you are correct is that you're cleansing
the קודש *Kodesh*, but that's a discussion for another time. Okay, so
anyway, let's take a look. גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this. Okay.
הדרן עלך כל הזבחים שנתערבו *Hadran Alach Kol Hazvachim Shenit'arvu*. So that
was the end of that פרק *perek*, which was a lot of
fun, which had a, like I said, with a lot of issues
about mixtures and תערובות *ta'arovot*. Okay, and then in the end we
got to this question about an inner חטאת chatat *chatas* and so
on, but the earlier stuff was like big stuff in terms of
תערובות *ta'arovot*. Okay, now we get onto a completely different discussion. Yes.
I know it's an aside, but the thing about the פר *par*,
isn't there some link because isn't that the only other
offering where the clothes become טמא Tamei *tamei* after you burn it?
No, I mean, well it's a general הלכה halacha *halacha* like we
said that a, I mean it is true, you are right that
this whole thing, I mean I think the מנחת *Minchat*... ספר החינוך
*Sefer Hachinuch* already asks this question or somebody already asked this question.
Like we go to this whole thing about the paradox of the
פרה אדומה *Parah Adumah*, that it causes טומאה *tumah*, you know, and
it and it causes טהרה *tahara*, it's מטהר *metaher* whatever. But people
say this is not really unique to קרבנות Korbanot *korbanot*. I mean,
well the idea that it causes טהרה *tahara* is a unique feature
of the פרה אדומה *Parah Adumah*. But the idea that when you
handle it, you become טמא *tamei*, we find that by like a
lot of קרבנות *korbanot*. So it's not... yeah, but you're right, but
it's the putting the two together, but the fact that handling it
makes you טמא *tamei* is not a unique feature to that. All
right, now we go on to the next פרק *perek*, which is
a different הלכה halacha, *halacha*, which is something that we've dealt with,
you know, sprinkled throughout the מסכת *masechet*, but here we're going to
deal with it directly. What? Sprinkled, right. Probably. Anyway, המזבח מקדש hamizbe'ach
mekadesh. את הראוי לו Harauy Lo *Hamizbeach mekadesh et haraui lo*. Okay,
the altar sanctifies things that are fit for it, which is basically
going to be the rule that even some things that are invalid,
if you put them on the altar, you don't take them off.
This is a rule that we've been dealing with since the beginning
of the מסכת *masechet*. Here we're going to deal with it directly
and figure out the scope. Now what constitutes הראוי לו *haraui lo*?
So this is a debate. רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua *Rabbi Yehoshua* אומר
*omer* כל הראוי לאישים *kol haraui l'ishim*. It has to be something,
okay, meaning it's obviously implicit it means something that maybe is invalid
and doesn't belong. I mean, if it belongs, of course you're going
to keep it up on the altar. But he's saying, okay, but
it's limited, fit, what does that exclude? It excludes things that don't
belong on the fire. What doesn't belong on the fire? Well, like
the pouring of the wine, for example. Okay, that would be something
that doesn't belong on the fire. Or the blood. You put the
blood at the top of the altar, okay, and you didn't sprinkle
it yet, or whatever the case might be. I don't know, whatever.
Anyway, so, okay, so the liquids that don't go on the fire,
that he would exclude. אם עלה לא ירד *Im ala lo yered*.
If that gets put up, if it does belong on the fire,
once it's on the altar, it stays up... stays on, okay, שנאמר
היא העולה hi ha-olah, על מוקדה al-mokedah *she'ne'emar Hi ha'olah al mokdah*.
So this is where we learn the idea that things stay on
the fire, okay, it is on the, it is the עולה Olah,
*olah*, it is on
the fire, the... what's the word מוקדה mokedah, *mokdah*? the conflagration, no
that's not the word, anyway, the pyre, I guess. מה עולה Olah
שהיא ראויה לאישים אם עלתה לא תרד *Mah olah she'hi re'uyah l'ishim
im altah lo tered*. So the same way an עולה Olah *olah*
belongs on the fire, he also could have stressed the word מוקדה
mokedah *mokdah*. אף כל שהוא ראוי לאישים rauy l'ishim אם עלה לא
תרד *Af kol she'hu ra'ui l'ishim im ala lo tered*. So היא
העולה על המזבח *Hi ha'olah al hamizbeach*. The עולה olah *olah* stays
on the מזבח mizbe'ach? *mizbeach*. Okay, so the עולה olah, *olah* means
anything that gets brought up if it is like an עולה olah
*olah* or if it belongs על המוקדה *al hamokdah*, if it is
something that goes on the fire, it stays up, even if it's
found to be פסול Pasul *pasul*. Okay, רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel, *Rabban
Gamliel* אומר *omer* כל הראוי למזבח l'mizbeach, אם עלה לא ירד *kol
haraui lamizbeach im ala lo yered* שנאמר היא העולה *she'ne'emar hi ha'olah*.
So he says, he doesn't say כל הראוי לאישים *kol haraui l'ishim*,
he says כל הראוי למזבח *kol haraui lamizbeach*. Okay, so something that
goes on the altar. So that includes not only things that go
on the fire, but even things like blood and wine, they also
belong on the altar. Okay, so even those don't come down. שנאמר
היא העולה על מוקדה al-mokedah על המזבח *she'ne'emar hi ha'olah al mokdah
al hamizbeach*. מה עולה olah שהיא ראויה למזבח אם עלתה לא תרד
*Mah olah she'hi re'uyah lamizbeach im altah lo tered*, I don't emphasize
that it's fit for the fire, I emphasize that it belongs on
the altar, אף כל דבר שהוא ראוי למזבח rauy l'mizbeach אם עלה
לא תרד *af kol davar she'hu ra'ui lamizbeach im ala lo tered*.
אין בין דברי רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel לדברי רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua,
*Ein bein divrei Rabban Gamliel l'divrei Rabbi Yehoshua* אלא הדם והנסכים *ela
hadam vehanesachim*. What their debate boils down to is the blood and
the and the and the wine. שרבן גמליאל אומר לא ירדו *She'Rabban
Gamliel omer lo yerdu*, don't come down if they're פסול Pasul *pasul*,
ורבי יהושע אומר ירדו *ve'Rabbi Yehoshua omer yerdu*, they have to come
down if they are פסול Pasul. *pasul* because again they are not,
what do you call it? because they don't belong on the fire.
Now, before we continue, I just want to point out that the
question is, okay, so for רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel *Rabban Gamliel*, if
it is anything that belongs on the altar, what's excluded from the
word, from the idea of כל הראוי למזבח *kol haraui lamizbeach*? So
we'll see about that in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. But the other
fascinating thing I want to point out here is a textual point
which both רש"י Rashi *Rashi* and תוספות Tosafos *Tosafot* say, which is
you have a phrase called... כל הראוי למזבח, and then you have
a debate of רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua, and רבן גמליאל, Rabban Gamliel
what is meant by that phrase? So if you take a look,
we'll just read it in תוספות Tosafos, because it's easier to see
the תוספות, but רש"י already made the
point, okay, המזבח מקדש. רבי יהושע ורבן גמליאל אתו לפרושי הכא רישא,
Rabbi Yehoshua v'Rabban Gamliel atu l'parushi hacha reisha, they're coming to explain
the meaning of the opening phrase of the
משנה. Mishnah. וכי האי גוונא בחזקת הבתים v'chi hai gavna b'chezkat habatim
we see this in another
גמרא Gemara דרבי ישמעאל ורבי עקיבא קמפרשי בסיפא חזקה דרישא. d'Rabbi Yishmael
v'Rabbi Akiva k'mparshi b'seifa chazaka d'reisha. In the beginning of the משנה
Mishnah it uses the word חזקה, chazaka, and then there's a debate
of תנאים Tannaim what the word is. So this is very important
because this gets to the history of the development of, you know,
our current משנה. Mishnah. That what, you know, what basically, I mean
academics have developed this point to basically teach like, you know, there's
often a debate of תנאים Tannaim is, you know, and is a
really debate of an early משנה Mishnah that was passed down, an
early teaching that was passed down that the terms were not fully
clarified. And then later תנאים Tannaim debate what those terms mean. So
there was a teaching, let's say from a hundred years ago, that
said
כל המזבח מקדש את הראוי לו, kol hamizbe'ach mekadesh et haraui lo,
okay, and everybody would repeat that teaching. And then by the time
you got to רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel. and רבי יהושע, Rabbi Yehoshua
they were debating like, wait, what does ראוי לו raui lo mean?
Does it mean for the fire? Does it mean for the מזבח?
Mizbeach So what they are debating is an earlier מסורה mesorah and
explaining those terms. And once you realize that, that that's embedded in
a משנה, Mishnah, because often the גמרא Gemara. obscures it by referring
to the first position as תנא קמא, Tanna Kamma, whereas really what's
happening is, is that they- is that it's an early משנה Mishnah
that they both inherited, and they're both debating what it means. And
you'll realize that you have this all the time. So for example,
in two opening משניות Mishnayot of two מסכתות, masechtos, just to digress
for a minute because we have a little bit of time. So
the first opening משנה Mishnah by פסחים Pesachim is
כל מקום שאין
מכניסין בו חמץ אין צריך בדיקה,
kol makom she'ein machnisin bo chametz ein
tzarich bdika, right? If you don't bring חמץ chametz there you don't
need בדיקה. bdika. And then it says ולמה v'lama or ובמה אמרו,
u'bameh amru, which is probably more likely ובמה אמרו, u'bameh amru, שתי
שורות במרתף. shtei shurot b'martef. This is explicitly making this point. So
one minute, so what's the context that if you don't- if when
you don't bring חמץ chametz in you don't have to check, what
is- in under what circumstances did they, did they say, so there
was an earlier teaching that you have to check the two like
rows of the wine cellar. So then you have
בית שמאי אומרים Beis Shammai omrim שתי שורות העליונות שהן החיצונות shtei
shurot ha'elyonot shehein hachitzonot whatever, ובית הלל אומרים, u'Beis Hillel omrim, you
know, שתי שורות shtei shurot blah blah blah. So they- so basically
you have an early teaching of שתי שורות במרתף shtei shurot b'martef
and בית הלל Beis Hillel and בית שמאי Beis Shammai are disagreeing
where are those שתי שורות? shtei shurot? What does that mean? So
בית הלל Beis Hillel and בית שמאי Beis Shammai is pretty darn
early, right? So here you see the משנה Mishnah explicitly references that
there's an earlier teaching and then there's a debate, right, what those
terms mean. Okay, like another- you people get that- another example of
this is the opening משנה Mishnah in גיטין. Gittin. The opening משנה
Mishnah in גיטין Gittin is המביא גט
ממדינת הים, hameivi get mim'dinat hayam, okay, from overseas, צריך שיאמר בפני
נכתב ובפני נחתם. tzarich sheyomar b'fanai nichtav uv'fanai nechtam. You have to
make a declaration that it was signed and sealed in front of
you. Okay, and then you have basically, I'm now forgetting exactly the
משנה, Mishnah, רבי אליעזר אומר, Rabbi Eliezer omer, I'd have to look
it up on my phone. Sorry.
Let's see who can get the first משנה Mishnah of גיטין Gittin
first?
משנה, Mishnah, נשים, Nashim, גיטין. Gittin. Okay, here we go. So
רבן גמליאל אומר Rabban Gamliel omer אף המביא מן הרקם ומן הגגר,
af hameivi min harekem u'min
hageger, wherever those places
are, רבי אליעזר אומר Rabbi Eliezer omer המביא מכפר
לודים
ללוד,
hameivi
mikfar
ludim
l'lud,
וחכמים אומרים v'chachamim omrim
אינו צריך אלא המביא ממדינת הים. eino tzarich ela hameivi mim'dinat hayam.
Okay, so like it seems like it's a four-way debate. First you
say if you bring it from מדינת הים, medinat hayam, רבן גמליאל
Rabban Gamliel says this, רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says this, חכמים Chachamim
say that, right? And then the גמרא Gemara, wants to know, wait
a minute, how's חכמים Chachamim different than this first thing? The חכמים
Chachamim say המביא ממדינת הים hameivi mim'dinat hayam that was this first
thing, okay? But what really is happening is is they all inherited
this first משנה Mishnah that says if you bring it from overseas
you have to say this. And then the question is what's overseas?
So רבן גמליאל says even if you bring from these little towns
that are right near ישראל, Yisrael, it's not way overseas, it's just
over the borderline, that's considered overseas. רבי אליעזר אומר Rabbi Eliezer omer
even if you bring from this little village outside of לוד, Lud,
that's considered overseas. And חכמים Chachamim say you have completely, you know,
redefined that term, overseas means overseas. It doesn't mean these places near
Israel. Okay, but anyway, the point being, the גמרא Gemara. says, wait
a minute, isn't this the same as this? And then it makes
some difference between them, and what's really happening is these later תנאים
Tanaim are a משנה Mishnah will start with an anonymous statement with
an undefined term and then the later תנאים Tanaim will debate what
those terms are because this is an early teaching that was inherited
and then this terms are debated. So that's like a really important
feature to recognize on משניות. Mishnayot. Yes.
So in in that case you have basically the generation at יבנה.
Yavne. Right. Here we have the first generation with the same rabbis
who are also the first generation after the destruction of the temple.
Right. So there may have been a break there.
Oh, that's an interesting point. But in the case I gave you
about the פסח, Pesach, about the חמץ, Chametz, that was בית הלל
בית
שמאי.
Beis Hillel
Beis Shammai. Okay. All right. So now let's take a look at
the גמרא. Gemara I'm sorry, we didn't finish the משנה. Mishnah.
It would seem that if it really meant the אישים, Ishim, it
would have been or should have been more explicit because מזבח Mizbeach.
sounds מזבח. Mizbeach, Yeah, but of course when I just tell you
something it belongs on the מזבח, Mizbeach, I your natural sense although
it's true דם Dam is what makes the קרבן, Korban, the first
thing you would think about I think about is burning on the
fire, right? That's where more of the action is happening. But yes,
I understand your point. Okay. Okay, רבי שמעון אומר, Rabbi Shimon Omer,
הזבח כשר והנסכים פסולים. Hazevach kasher vehanesachim psulim. Now רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon has a different structure, has a different approach. He says fundamentally
I agree that this applies even to things that don't go on
the fire. It applies to the wine offerings. But here's my new
criteria. It's only something like an עולה, olah this isn't explicit it'll
be explicit in the גמרא, Gemara it's only something like an עולה
olah that's brought on its own account, not something that is brought
by virtue of something else. So by the wine for example, okay,
it would depend. If you bring wine as an independent sacrifice, so
and you put it up on the מזבח, Mizbeach. even if it's
פסול Pasul, don't take it down. But if you're bringing the wine
because it accompanies a קרבן, Korban, then if it's פסול Pasul bring
it down. Okay. So for him the criteria is not wine versus
something that's burnt. For him the criterion is: is it coming on
its own accord or coming by virtue of something else.
Okay, so like the שתי הלחם Shtei Halechem for instance.
Yeah, שתי הלחם Shtei Halechem well, שתי הלחם Shtei Halechem doesn't go
on the מזבח. Mizbeach, הזבח כשר והנסכים פסולים, Hazevach kasher vehanesachim psulim,
הנסכים כשרים והזבח פסול. Hanesachim ksherim vehazevach pasul. He says I don't
care whatever the scenario is, the קרבן Korban is כשר Kasher but
something happened to the wine, it got- something טמא touched it. Or
the wine is כשר Kasher but the קרבן Korban is פסול. In
that case you don't bring the wine because the wine only comes
by virtue of the קרבן. Korban. אפילו זה וזה פסולים, Afilu zeh
vezeh psulim, or both are פסול, הזבח לא ירדו והנסכים ירדו. Hazevach
lo yerdu vehanesachim yerdu. ירד והנסכים ירדו. Yered vehanesachim yerdu. So the
קרבן Korban stays up, the wine goes down. So wine on its
own, if it's coming as its separate sacrifice, stay up. But something
that's coming by virtue of something else, if it's invalid, it goes
down. Okay, so three different opinions what the criteria is. Let's take
a look at the גמרא. Gemara Top of פג עמוד ב. Pei
Gimmel Amud Bais. הראוי לו אין שאין הראוי לו לא. Harauy lo
in she'ein harauy lo lo. Okay, so now let's figure out what
is what's not fit for it. Now later we're going to have
a discussion about how bad of an invalidity, like is it רובע
ונרבע, Rova Venirva, an animal using bestiality for example, or an animal
had a מום Mum before it even got, you know, to the
בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. It was already פסול way before. So that's
going to be like later משניות. Mishnayot. But the גמרא Gemara understands
that this phrase of הראוי לו seems to be not about how
bad of an invalidity it is, it seems to be describing how
connected it is to the מזבח, Mizbeach, right? Because we're discussing does
it go on the fire or does it just go on the
מזבח, Mizbeach? right? So when so we get the opinion that says
fire. That's excluding נסכים Nesachim and blood. But what about the opinion
that includes נסכים Nesachim and blood, says anything connected to the מזבח?
Mizbeach? So what is not connected to the מזבח? Mizbeach Okay, that
you would want to keep on it. Obviously like, you know, I
could put my hat on the מזבח Mizbeach but obviously there there's
not a point. You know, what is the type of thing that
you would want to keep on the מזבח Mizbeach. but is not
connected, especially according to the opinion that includes everything even wine and
oil, okay, even wine and blood. So what does that exclude? So
שאין הראוי לו למעוטי מאי? She’ein harauy lo lema’utei mai? אמר רב
פפא Amar Rav Pappa למעוטי קמצים שלא קידשו בכלי. Lema’utei kmetzim shelo
kidshu bkeli. So here's what it is: when you took a hand
breadth from the מנחה, Mincha, that's your קומץ, Kometz, and normally what
you do afterwards is you put it in a כלי Keli to
sanctify it and to make it fit for being brought on the
מזבח. Mizbeach But instead you just went straight and you put it
on the מזבח Mizbeach. without putting it in that כלי. Keli. That
you have to take off. Why is that different than everything else?
Because everything else is all like you know if I go ahead
and I bring this cow to the to the בית המקדש, Beis
Hamikdash, right, you know from the beginning which parts are going on
the מזבח. Mizbeach. The blood, the entrails, if it's an עולה olah,
the meat, right? You know exactly you could label, you know, you
know you've got those things which is like those butcher's cuts, you
have a picture of a cow and it has... so you could
write already before anything is done know exactly which parts are going
to the מזבח. Mizbeach? Okay. Whereas whereas
here by a מנחה, Mincha, which part of which part of this
מנחה Mincha is going to the מזבח? Mizbeach You tell me. I
don't know. It depends where you're going to take the קומץ Kometz
from. So it is not yet designated as be- you don't- the
thing that's going to the מזבח mizbeach, has yet to be designated.
Now you could say from the moment you did the קומץ Kometz
it's designated. but they're going to say no, because there, what makes
that then, since it wasn't designated yet, what fully makes it designated
for the altar is the putting in the vessel. Okay now because
you could say other things also need a vessel. I got to
catch the blood in a vessel. I can't put the blood on
the altar without catching it in a vessel whatever. That might be
true, but at least you knew it was the blood that was
going there. Here, you didn't know which part of it, okay, and
therefore it's all for that part to be seen as final as
getting labeled and seen as relevant for the altar, you need to
take the קומץ kometz and then sanctify it by putting it in
the vessel. So if you put that the קומץ kometz on the
altar before putting it in the vessel, that would have to come
down. Okay, that's the type of thing that's not fit for the
altar even if you it have a more expansive definition to include
blood and wine.
Yes, practical thing. So I had this unsanctified flour combination and I
throw it onto the altar of fire.
I
didn't get it off anyway.
How do I get it off? It's burning.
Yes, okay fine. The point is that this stuff doesn't have to
be directly burning on the fire, it could be up there near
the fire, and it could be up there and then whatever right,
yeah.
Wait, let's let's interesting question also. So we say ראוי לאישים rauy
l'ishim versus ראוי למזבח but they're actually the same, so ראוי לאישים
rauy l'ishim, when you put it in the fire as opposed to
putting anywhere למזבח, it's they both agree by putting anywhere in the
מזבח, mizbeach even if it's not on the fire.
Yes, we're going to get to that later, meaning when we say,
even if you say ראוי לאישים, rauy l'ishim, it's not you're describing
the type of thing that gets to stay up, but if you
put it let's say on the ramp or you put it on
the top of the altar without putting it yet on the fire,
it still gets to stay there because it is ראוי לאישים, that
is correct. It is not where it's being put, it's what type
of an object it is.
If the קומץ kometz wasn't in a vessel, how is it being
carried to the altar?
With your hand.
Just he's walking up just like that all the way and he
never sanctified?
Yep, exactly. Okay, or he put it in some other vessel but
not a כלי שרת. kli shares. Okay. So,
so מסקיף ליה רבינא, maskif le-Ravina, רבינא Ravina challenges, מאי שנא מעולא?
mai shna me'ulla? One minute, how is this different than עולא? Ulla?
The how is this קמצים kmatzim which you say have to go
down different than the following case of עולא? Ulla? דאמר עולא, de-amar
Ulla, because עולא Ulla says, אימורי קדשים קלים שהעלם לפני זריקת דמים.
emurei kodshim kalim she-he'alam lifnei zrikas damam. Let's take another case. The
אימורים emurim of the of קדשים קלים, kodshim kalim, of a שלמים
shlamim that you put up before you threw the blood. So similarly
before the blood is thrown, these are not yet ready to be
on the altar.
Okay now, why קדשים קלים? kodshim kalim? Okay, anything isn't ready to
be on the altar because this is similar to the idea of
that it's not yet designated to the מזבח mizbeach in the following
way. It's a little different than the מנחה. mincha. By, as I
said, by a normal animal you know exactly which part is going
on the altar, and here too you know the אימורים emurim are
going, but by קדשים קלים kodshim kalim what is even though you
know which part, they're not yet fully sanctified. There's no מעילה me'ila
by a שלמים, shlamim, okay, because fundamentally a שלמים shlamim is still
like the owner's meat, he's going to eat it or whatever, it's
not seen as fundamentally out of his control. That's why it's קדשים
קלים. kodshim kalim. Okay, and therefore there's no מעילה. me'ila. Even if
it, even if you got if you got those אימורים emurim before
the blood was thrown and you benefited from those אימורים, emurim, you
would not transgress מעילה. me'ila. Because since fundamentally the animal remains under
the owner's control, even the אימורים emurim which are eventually going to
go on the altar are not yet seen as God's portion as
the altar's portion until they're ready, until the blood is thrown. That's
that is the thing that takes them out of the owner's control
and makes them like fully God's. Okay, so in that way even
though you know which part, it's not yet fully שייך shayach to
the altar until the blood is thrown because it's under the owner's
control. So it's a little different than the מנחה mincha as a
חטאת even though it's not fit to be put because the blood
hasn't been thrown, the animal is still fundamentally starts under God's control.
Okay, and since it starts under God's control, that's considered that it
was הוברר חלקו של מזבח, huvrar chelko shel mizbeach, the portion of
the altar has been already designated. So in the case of the
מנחה mincha which is קדשי קדשים, kodshei kodashim, you it is fully
under God's control but you don't know which portion you're talking about
yet. Right here you know which portion you're talking about but it's
not yet fully under the מזבח's mizbeach. control. So the גמרא Gemara
says in either way it's not yet fully designated for the מזבח.
Mizbeach So why is one case you gets to stay on the
top and the other it doesn't? So of course you could say
exactly this difference because in one case it's just an issue about
how sanctified it's been, the other it's a case of whether you've
even designated it properly. But let's see what the גמרא Gemara says.
And this is a very interesting philosophical implication which I have to
process. Okay. No, seriously, like you know, you are מקדיש makdish it
but then it comes out of your control in one case entirely
in you know versus staying in your
control right exactly
all right you'll think it through. Okay, so anyway the גמרא Gemara,
says like this, אימורי קדשים קלים שהעלם לפני זריקת דמים לא ירדו,
emurei kodshim kalim she-he'alam lifnei zrikas damam lo yerdu, נעשה לחמו של
מזבח. na'asa lachmo shel mizbeach. They are because have become already the
the bread of the you know of the altar that's quoting obviously
echoing a biblical verse, right, לחם אשה lechem isheh etc. So הנהו
hanoch but it's also by the way you know because it's very
it's very interesting the way חז"ל Chazal have reframed things to remove
some of the anthropomorphisms of the פסוקים. pesukim. It's not God's bread,
it's the altar's bread. What? Less extreme. I know. Anyway so the
גמרא Gemara says no, הנהו לא מחסרו מעשה בגופייהו. hanoch lo mechasru
ma'aseh be-gufayhu.
The difference is the following: by the אימורים, Emurim, you don't have
to do something to the אימורים Emurim yet. It's true. It's not
yet fully designated as the altar's portion because it's not yet fully
into God's control as it were. Okay, but the actual אימורים Emurim
themselves, it's about something that you have to do outside of the
אימורים, Emurim, something you have to do with the blood. So since
as far as the אימורים Emurim themselves are concerned,
they're in the state they need to be, so that's considered enough
to keep them on the altar. Whereas by the מנחה, Mincha, by
the קומץ, Kometz, it hasn't yet, it didn't start, it hasn't been
designated to begin with, and the designation of the object itself hasn't
finished. Right, because you have to actually put this קומץ Kometz into
a כלי. Kli. So therefore this is seen as more one step
removed from the altar, right, than the אימורים Emurim are. Since it's
true the אימורים Emurim are not yet halachically allowed to, but nothing
is missing in the אימורים. Emurim. Nothing, something is missing in terms
of the blood. Okay, so that's the difference. But again, it is
interesting those differences that
in
one case the problem is that it's not yet fully sanctified as
it were, it's not yet fully under God's portion, the מזבח mizbeach...
portion, and the other, the problem was less the קדושה Kedusha and
more the designation about which part of this מנחה Mincha is going
to go up. Okay. So now we continue. רבי יהושע, Rabbi Yehoshua
so that's what would be excluded even for רבן גמליאל. רבי יהושע
אומר כל הראוי לאישים. Rabbi Yehoshua omer kol ha-raui la-ishim. Now רבי
יהושע excludes more. It has to be fit for the fire. So
let's see what the גמרא Gemara says. רבן גמליאל נמי הכתיב עולה
על מוקדה? Rabban Gamliel nami ha-ketiv olah al-mokedah? But it's not the
word עולה olah. that's significant presumably, although רבי יהושע mentioned the word
עולה, the keyword is מוקדה, mokedah. on the fire. So what does
he do with the word on the fire if he includes also
wine, also blood? ההוא לאדורי פקיעים הוא דאתא. Hahu l'adurei pekiyim hu
d'ata. What that's coming to tell you is not the הלכה halacha
about only things that belong on the fire. That's telling you a
separate הלכה, Halacha. that if you've got the logs of the firewood
and one of them sort
of gets flown off the fire, that you're supposed to put it
back. It's not allowing something to remain, it's obligating you that על
מוקדה keep the stuff on the fire. Like if something flies up,
if a log flies off, put it back on. Okay. ואידך לאדורי
פקיעים מנא ליה? V'idach, l'adurei pekiyim minaleh? Where does he get this
idea? נפקא ליה מאשר תאכל האש. Nafkeh leh me'asher tachal ha-esh. That
the fire consumes. So as רש״י Rashi says, we know it's because
it speaks about taking the ashes. So why do you have to
say the ashes that the fire consumes? Of course if it's ashes
the fire consumed it, although we learn other things from that like
it has to be really burnt. But anyway, so it means that
things that are being eaten by the fire have to somehow stay
on the fire. That's what we learn from it. So if it
flies off, put it back on. ואידך, V'idach, wait a minute. ההוא
מיבעי ליה לאכולי עולה
אתה מחזיר ואי אתה מחזיר אכולי קטרת. Hahu mibaye leh l'achulei olah
atah machazir v'ei atah machazir achulei ketoret. No, it says אשר תאכל
האש, asher tachal ha-esh, so that the fire consumes, but it says
היא העולה, עולה על המזבח, olah al-mizbeach, and אשר תאכל האש. asher
tachal ha-esh. So the combination of עולה and תאכל האש tachal ha-esh
means
that
only things like an עולה that fly off you have to put
back on,
but let's say קטרת. ketoret. Now the reason קטרת ketoret is different
is קטרת ketoret doesn't belong on the outer altar.
קטרת ketoret belongs on the inner altar. So if קטרת ketoret flew
off, you don't put it back on. דתני רבי חנינא בר מניומי
בן רבי אליעזר בן יעקב אשר תאכל האש את העולה על המזבח,
De-tani Rabbi Chanina bar Minyumi ben Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov asher tachal
ha-esh et
ha-olah al ha-mizbeach, אכולי עולה אתה מחזיר ואי אתה מחזיר אכולי קטרת.
achulei olah atah machazir v'ei atah machazir achulei ketoret. Not קטרת, ketoret,
that you wouldn't put back. ואידך, V'idach, and the other one would
say where does he learn that out from? לאו ממילא שמעת מינה
דאכולי עולה מהדרינן. Lav mimila shemana minah d'achulei olah mahadrinan. Fine. Okay,
so it says that you put the עולה back and not the
קטרת, ketoret, and that implicitly it's also telling you you do put
the עולה back, which means the stuff that flies off generally you
put back, with the exception of the קטרת. ketoret. So whatever, we
go through the various accounting. I still remember many many years ago
I was teaching once a גמרא, Gemara it says what does he
do with this פסוק, pasuk what does he do, what does he
do, and we go through until you finally get to some resolution.
So anyway, so I said yes, the גמרא Gemara is just like
working through the math. So I had somebody in my class who
was a mathematician and she said, "Math? That's not math. That's accounting!"
So anyway,
yes, Michael?
"Do we say that this is a מצוה דאורייתא? mitzvah d'oraita? Like
in other words,
if this rabbi let's say were to tally up his 613 מצות,
mitzvot, one of them would be to like put back stuff that
the מזבח..."
"Not every הלכה Halacha. that you learn from a פסוק pasuk counts
as a מצוה."
mitzvah. "Right. So I'm saying is it more of an אסמכתא asmachta
or..."
"No, it's not an אסמכתא, asmachta, it's a general question like do
you learn details? Every single thing the Torah says to do with
the blood of an עולה, is that a separate מצוה mitzvah of
תרי״ג מצות? taryag mitzvot? You'd have a lot more מצות. mitzvot. No,
one of the first רמב״ם Rambam's כללים kelalim in his הקדמה hakdama
to ספר המצות Sefer HaMitzvot is you don't count details. And the
question is which details are just the specifics of the bigger מצוה
mitzvah of bringing an עולה. Okay. So here too a lot of
these things could be just read as details, as procedures, not necessarily
as a מצוה. mitzvah. Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara continues. Anyway,
that's it. You stress the פסוק that says על מוקדה or do
you learn מוקדה to tell you something else? רבן גמליאל אומר כל
הראוי, Rabban Gamliel omer kol ha-raui, so רבן גמליאל says I don't
focus on the word מוקדה. I focus, I say anything that belongs
on the מזבח *mizbeach*. רבי יהושע נמי הכתיב מזבח *Rabbi Yehoshua nami
haksiv mizbeach*. It says היא העולה על המזבח *hi haolah al hamizbeach*,
על מוקדה *al mokdah*, no, it says היא העולה על מה הפסוק
היא העולה על מוקדה על המזבח *hi haolah al mah hapasuk hi
haolah al mokdah al hamizbeach*, right? So doesn't it say מזבח *mizbeach*?
So isn't it enough that it's relevant to the מזבח *mizbeach*? Why
don't you have a broader definition? So he says נמי הכתיב המזבח
והוא מבעי ליה מאי קאמר רחמנא כל הראוי למוקדה מקדש מזבח *nami
haksiv hamizbeach vehu mibaye lei mai kaamar rachmana kol harauy lemokdah mekadesh
mizbeach*. So it's a little, grammar's a little funny, but what it
means is is that like Michael said before, it doesn't have to
be on the fire to stay on the fire. מוקדה *Mokdah* tells
you it has to be something that's going on the fire, but
when does it get to stay on המזבח *hamizbeach*? As soon as
you put it on המזבח *hamizbeach*. So it is the מזבח *mizbeach*
that sanctifies, it's not the fire that sanctifies. Yeah, there's a whole
discussion about that. Okay, so it's not the fire that sanctifies, it
is the מזבח *mizbeach*. So it's על המזבח *al hamizbeach*. If it's
on the מזבח *mizbeach*, it stays on the מזבח *mizbeach* even if
it's not on the fire. That's what the word מזבח *mizbeach* is
telling you. מוקדה *Mokdah* is telling you it's only for things that
belong on the fire. Okay, so different parts.
So this is regardless of which מזבח *mizbeach* you put it on
or only on המזבח *hamizbeach*?
Oh no, מזבח החיצון *mizbeach hachitzon*.
If you put it on מזבח הפנימי *mizbeach hapnimi*, right? You shouldn't
have and that's it, it's not מקדש *mekadesh* anything.
ואידך מזבח אחרינא כתיב *veidach mizbeach achrina ksiv*. The other one says
it says מזבח *mizbeach* twice. What does it say? היא העולה על
מוקדה על המזבח כל הלילה עד הבוקר ואש המזבח תוקד בו *hi
haolah al mokdah al hamizbeach kol halaila ad haboker veesh hamizbeach tukad
bo*. So one מזבח *mizbeach* tells you the מזבח *mizbeach* is what
sanctifies, and the other מזבח *mizbeach* is telling you that it's anything
that belongs on the מזבח *mizbeach*, even wine and blood. ואידך חד
דהוה ליה שעת הכושר וחד דלא הוה ליה שעת הכושר *veidach chad
dehava lei shas hachosher vechad dela hava lei shas hachosher*. The other
מזבח *mizbeach* is telling you, and this is what we haven't gotten
to yet, the degree of the פסול *psul*, that even certain types
of things that are פסול *pasul* before they ever became fit. What
would be the example? Like if I שחט *shachted* something and caught
the blood and then the blood became טמא *tamei*, so the blood
had a שעת הכושר *shas hachosher*, right? It could have been fit.
Or the meat, it was fit, or you know, and then it
became טמא *tamei* afterwards. There could be something that never had a
שעת הכושר *shas hachosher*. I slaughtered it with a thought of פיגול
*pigul*. So then it never became sanctified as soon as it became
meat or blood or entrails, it was already פסול *pasul*. So the
extra מזבח *mizbeach* is telling you, so now we're getting into the
question of what type of פסול *psul* we're talking about, that even
things with a פסול *psul* that were never fit for the מזבח
*mizbeach*. Okay, you know their פסול *psul* started before they didn't even
have a moment where they could have been brought on the מזבח
*mizbeach*. Okay. ואידך כיון דפסולין נינהו ורבינהו רחמנא *veidach kivan depsulin ninhu
verabinhu rachmana*. The other would say, since they're פסולים *psulim* and the
רחמנא *Rachmana* included them, I don't need a separate פסוק *pasuk*. Once
the תורה *Torah* is telling me that even invalid things are allowed
to stay on the altar, לא שנא דהוה ליה שעת הכושר לא
שנא דלא הוה ליה שעת הכושר *lo shana dehava lei shas hachosher
lo shana dela hava lei shas hachosher*. I would have no basis
for distinguishing. You're saying, 'Wait, I don't know to include all types
of things. Maybe it makes a difference if there was a moment
that it was fit or not fit.' So the other one says,
'I don't know. Once the תורה *Torah* is telling me this brand
new novel idea that things that are פסול *pasul* can stay on
the מזבח *mizbeach*, then that should apply to all things. Why should
I distinguish between these types of two categories?' Okay, so in the
end, of course, they all agree to the הלכה Halacha *halacha*. The
question is just how you get it. But the important point is,
as was pointed out before by Michael, which is even if you
say it has to be something fit for the fire, it's not
that it has to be on the fire to stay up. The
מזבח *mizbeach* is מקדש *mekadesh* it. Now
we
get to the position of רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon* that focuses on
whether it's coming on its own account or on account of something
else. רבי שמעון אומר הזבח כשר תניא רבי שמעון אומר עולה *Rabbi
Shimon omer hazevach kasher tanya Rabbi Shimon omer olah*. מה עולה הבאה
בגלל עצמה *mah olah habaa biglal atzmah*. So he doesn't focus on
עולה *olah* whether it means fire or מזבח *mizbeach*. He says, he
focuses on the word עולה *olah* to mean it's coming on its
own accord. מה עולה הבאה בגלל עצמה אף כל הבאים בגלל עצמן
*mah olah habaa biglal atzmah af kol habaim biglal atzman*. יצאו נסכים
Nesachim, הבאים בגלל זבח Zavach. *yatzu nesachim habaim biglal zevach*. Like excludes
the wine offerings that come on account of the זבח Zavach, *zevach*
or also the flour and oil that come on account of the
זבח *zevach*. So if you bring flour and oil as a מנחה
*mincha*, it's and it's פסול *pasul* it stays up. If you bring
it as a מנחת נסכים Minchas Nesachim, *minchas nesachim* and it's פסול
*pasul* it comes down. רבי יוסי הגלילי אומר מתוך שנאמר *Rabbi Yosi
HaGlili omer mitoch sheneemar*. So now we have and this is going
to be fun because the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s going to show us
based on their different criteria, it's going to go through different scenarios.
Right, like if it's a wine, is there a way of getting
it off?
So let's deal with everybody's different criteria. Okay. Well, no, you put
the, well okay, I'll make my point. So anyway, so you could
put the wine in a vessel and put it on the top
of the altar. You haven't poured it yet. It became פסול *pasul*,
it became טמא *tamei*, you put it on the top and you
didn't pour it yet. Okay. So anyway, so we have
רבי יהושע *Rabbi Yehoshua*, רבן גמליאל *Rabban Gamliel*, right? Was he the
other one in the משנה *Mishnah*? Yep. Okay, now we have who's
the third one we just dealt with?
We have רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon*.
רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon*. Okay, so let's deal what their reasonings are.
So רבן גמליאל *Rabban Gamliel*, רבי יהושע *Rabbi Yehoshua* says anything that
is fit for the fire.
Okay, he says everything basically.
Even wine and blood. Okay with the example, with the exception of,
you know,
the. That's his definition. Okay, now let's keep on going. Okay, and
then we're going to test it, we're going to apply certain things
and see how it's going to fall out. Okay. רבי יוסי הגלילי
אומר *Rabbi Yose HaGlili omer*, מתוך שנאמר *mitosh ne'emar* כל הנוגע במזבח
יקדש *kol hanogeah bamizbe'ach yikdash*, whatever touches this מזבח *mizbe'ach* becomes sanctified,
שומע אני בין ראוי בין שאינו ראוי *shome'ani bein ra'uy bein she'eino
ra'uy*, maybe if it has no relevance to the מזבח *mizbe'ach*. תלמוד
לומר כבשים בני שנה *Talmud lomar kevasim bnei shana*. מה כבשים *Ma
kevasim* is the next פסוק *pasuk*, וזאת אשר תעשה על המזבח *ve'zos
asher ta'aseh al hamizbe'ach*, you know, כבשים בני שנה *kevasim bnei shana*
to something, עולת תמיד *olat tamid*, whatever. מה כבשים ראויים אף כל
ראוי *Ma kevasim re'uyim af kol ra'uy*. It has to be like
a lamb, it has to be fit. What does that exclude? We'll
see in a minute. רבי עקיבא אומר *Rabbi Akiva omer*, עולה *olah*,
מה עולה ראויה אף כל ראוי *Ma olah re'uyah af kol ra'uy*.
No, anything like an עולה *olah*. So one says anything like כבשים
*kevasim*, one says anything like an עולה *olah*. מאי בינייהו *Mai beynaihu*?
אמר אבא בר אבא *Amar Abba bar Abba*, עולת עוף פסולה איכא
בינייהו *Olat of pesulah ika beynaihu*. What if it's a bird? מר
מייתי לה מעולה *Mar maitai lei me'olah*. If you learn from עולה
*olah*, it includes even birds. ומר מייתי לה מכבשים *Umar maitai lei
mikvasim*. And the other learns it from כבשים *kevasim*, so it's not
birds, only like sheep and cows etc. ולמאן דמייתי לה מכבשים *Uleman
dmaitai lei mikvasim*, הא כתיב עולה *Ha ksiv olah*? What does he
do with the עולה *olah* phrase? אי כתיב כבשים ולא כתיב עולה
*Ee ksiv kevasim velo ksiv olah*, הוה אמינא אפילו מחיה *Hava amina
afilu mechaya*, maybe even if it was something that was invalid from
life, even if it was a בעל מום *ba'al mum* or something
like that. כתב רחמנא עולה *Kasav rachmana olah*. So we're going to
get to that later, that a בעל מום *ba'al mum* is not
included. Okay, so it has to be like an עולה *olah*, I
mean it has to be something that basically is like, you know,
like an עולה *olah* in the sense that it is fit at
least to be a sacrifice, it wasn't invalid even when it was
alive. ולמאן דמייתי לה מעולה *Uleman dmaitai lei me'olah*, הא כתיב כבשים
*Ha ksiv kevasim*? What does כבשים *kevasim* come to exclude? אי כתיב
עולה ולא כתיב כבשים *Ee ksiv olah velo ksiv kevasim*, הוה אמינא
אפילו מנחה *Hava amina afilu mincha*. Because he's saying while I include
birds, it has to still be a living thing. I would not
include a מנחה *mincha*, an invalid מנחה *mincha* doesn't get to stay.
כתב רחמנא כבשים *Kasav rachmana kevasim*. Okay, כבשים *kevasim*. So now we
have the following position. So we got רבי יוסי הגלילי *Rabbi Yose
HaGlili*, okay, רבי יוסי הגלילי
*Rabbi Yose HaGlili* and we have רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva*, okay. So
רבי יוסי הגלילי *Rabbi Yose HaGlili* says focus on the word כבשים
*kevasim*, which basically means not birds or מנחה *mincha*, and רבי עקיבא
*Rabbi Akiva* says עולה *olah*, which means, you know, and כבשים *kevasim*
is sort of like there in the פסוק *pasuk*, so while he's
not going to exclude birds, he's going to just say not a
מנחה *mincha*. Okay, so you got all those different criteria and now
we're going to see where the...
so רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* is the most lenient then, right?
No, because
it has to be an animal.
Of those two, it's got to be an animal. Okay, these ones
are the more inclusive. Okay, this is the most inclusive, רבן גמליאל
*Rabban Gamliel*, okay. So רבן גמליאל *Rabban Gamliel* basically says everything. Now
let's see how it's going to play out, okay, with different cases.
So let's take a look. מאי איכא בין הני תנאי להני תנאי
*Mai ika bein hani tannai l'hani tannai* דמתניתין *d'masnisin*? So first of
all, what's the difference between them and these, the תנאי *tannai* of
the משנה *mishna*? אמר רב פפא *Amar Rav Pappa*, קמצים שקידשו בכלי
איכא בינייהו *Kmatzim shekideshu bikeli ika beynaihu*. You actually took the קומץ
*kometz* and you put it in a כלי *keli*, right? Meaning an
actual מנחה *mincha* itself, but actually when it's fit for the מזבח
*mizbe'ach*, you put it in a
כלי *keli*. So it became
פסול *pasul*. Right. קומץ שקידש בכלי
*Kometz shekidesh bikeli*. Okay. So yes, it belongs on the fire, obviously
yes. This is a bigger one. And you know, he only excludes
לא קידש בכלי *lo kidesh bikli*, right? רבי יהושע *Rabbi Yehoshua*, remember
because that's the whole thing of הופרש חלב *hufra chelev*. Okay, but
once it's קידש בכלי *kidesh bikeli*, it's totally fit. Yes, it's coming
on its own sake.
Well, it depends, was this a קומץ *kometz*? Do you still have
to do the...
no, you don't do a קומץ *kometz* of מנחת סוטה *minchas sotah*.
That means a real מנחה *mincha*. No and no. Okay, so that's
that debate. Okay, so איכא בינייהו *ika beynaihu*. לתנא דידן לא ירדו
*Le-tana didan lo yerdu*, doesn't come down because once it's put in
the כלי *keli*, it's fit for the altar. לתנא דמתניתין *Letana dimasnisin*,
this ברייתא *braita*, ירדו *yerdu* because for them it's only animals. Okay.
Now the גמרא *gemara* says, אמר ריש לקיש *Amar Reish Lakish*, מנחה
בא בפני עצמה *Mincha ba biphnei atzma* לדברי כולם לא תירד Teired.
*ledivrei kulam lo tiered*. לדברי רבי יוסי הגלילי *Ledivrei Rabbi Yose HaGlili*
ורבי עקיבא תירד *ve-Rabbi Akiva tiered*. So a מנחה *mincha* that comes
by itself, okay, which is exactly now this is really the same
point, that's קומץ שקידש בכלי *kometz shekidesh bikeli*, that's a מנחה *mincha*
that comes by itself. Okay. So, or but he might here mean
like a מנחת נסכים Minchas Nesachim, *minchas nesachim* because you can bring
a מנחה *mincha* exactly what you would bring that would come with,
you know, the wine and the oil and whatever, but bring it
like that would normally come with a קרבן Korban. *korban* and you
bring it by itself. You're allowed to do
this. Okay, so it's essentially the same point. מנחת הבאה בפני עצמה
*Minchas haba'ah biphnei atzma*. Okay. So it's basically the same point. It's
a מנחה *mincha*, so yes yes yes, it's coming on its own
sake. sake, but for them, no and no because it's a מנחה.
That's essentially the same as the previous one. Now, מנחה הבאה עם
הזבח. Minchah HaBaah Im HaZavach. Okay, so now מנחת... so yeah, let's
just do if it's עם הזבח. Im HaZavach. Okay, we're going
to... running out of space. Okay, so then yes, yes, and here
he's a no, right? Because it's not coming on its own accord.
Okay. So, מנחה הבאה עם הזבח Minchah HaBaah Im HaZavach לדברי רבן
גמליאל ורבי יהושע לא תירד. LeDivrei Rabban Gamliel VeRabbi Yehoshua Lo Teired.
So for these two, it doesn't come down and לדברי כולן, LeDivrei
Kullan, whoever once you're three you're
כולן, Kullan, everybody
else תירד. Okay. נסכים הבאים בפני עצמן. Nesachim HaBaim Bifnei Atzman. How
about נסכים, Nesachim not the מנחת נסכים, Minchas Nesachim not the flour
and the water, but actually the liquid, I mean the wine. Okay,
so that's בפני עצמן Bifnei Atzman and then it's עם הזבח. Im
HaZavach,
Okay, just the wine.
Okay, so...
You just put that in
parentheses, so what part? Wine, נסכים Nesachim, wine. 'Cause you know, I
always think of... Right, fine. מנחת נסכים, Minchas Nesachim flour
and oil.
You know wine, we know יין. Yayin.
Right. נסכים הבאים בפני עצמן, Nesachim HaBaim Bifnei Atzman, where am I?
הבאים בפני עצמן, HaBaim Bifnei Atzman, לדברי כולן ירדו. LeDivrei Kullan Yerdu.
לדברי רבן גמליאל ורבי שמעון לא ירדו. LeDivrei Rabban Gamliel VeRabbi Shimon
Lo Yerdu. So here, okay, נסכים, Nesachim so here he becomes a
no because it's not for the fire. Okay, and I should have
reversed these whatever because this is the most inclusive but anyway. Okay,
but here he says yes, he includes wine and it's because it's
בפני עצמן Bifnei Atzman he says yes. Okay. And they basically say
no and no because it's not an animal. Okay. So that's לדברי
כולן ירדו, LeDivrei Kullan Yerdu, everybody, I mean three of them. לדברי
רבן גמליאל ורבי שמעון לא ירדו. LeDivrei Rabban Gamliel VeRabbi Shimon Lo
Yerdu. Everybody getting this? Right, here it doesn't go down because he
doesn't care that it's liquid and he doesn't care that it's liquid
as long as it's coming on its own sake.
נסכים הבאים עם הזבח, Nesachim HaBaim Im HaZavach, לדברי כולן ירדו, LeDivrei
Kullan Yerdu, לדברי רבן גמליאל לחודיי לא ירדו. LeDivrei Rabban Gamliel LeChudei
Lo Yerdu. Only Rabban Gamliel is okay...
Excuse me, only
Rabban Gamliel is okay 'cause if it's עם הזבח, they say it
goes down because it's not an animal. He says it goes... Rabbi
Shimon says it goes down 'cause it's not coming on its own
sake. He says it's coming down because it's not for the fire.
The only one who says it doesn't come down is Rabban Gamliel
who doesn't care that it's not on the fire and doesn't care
that it's not coming on its own sake and doesn't care that
it's not an animal. Okay, everybody get that? Alright.
So, פשיטא. Pshita. Now the גמרא says that was all a lovely
chart but we could have done that ourselves. I mean it was
nice that you worked it through for us but it didn't tell
us any new הלכה. Alright, I also say so what, a good
illustration is always helpful. Anyway, the גמרא says מנחה הבאה בפני עצמה
איצטריכא ליה. Minchah HaBaah Bifnei Atzmah Itztricha Lei. No, because since it
gave the example of a מנחת נסכים Minchas Nesachim that came by
itself, that was a חידוש Chiddush that you could bring a מנחת
נסכים by itself without bringing it together with a קרבן. Korban. וכההיא
דרבא, U'Kehahi DeRava, like Rava. דאמר רבא, DeAmar Rava, מתנדב אדם מנחת
נסכים בכל יום. Misnadeiv Adam Minchas Nesachim BeChol Yom. You can bring
a מנחת נסכים by itself even without bringing it as part of
a קרבן. Korban. So the גמרא says no, ונישמעינהו כדרבא. VeNishmeinhu KeDeRava.
If that's all you wanted to tell us, don't tell us this
whole thing, just say, hey, by the way, you should know we
פסקן Pasken like Rava about this הלכה. So the גמרא says fine,
נסכים הבאים עם הזבח איצטריכא ליה. Nesachim HaBaim Im HaZavach Itztricha Lei.
Fine, the חידוש Chiddush is the נסכים that came with the זבח.
דקמיקרב להו למחר ויומא אחרא DeKamikrav Lehu LeMachar VeYoma Achra
because when we're saying here that when they come with the זבח,
they're considered not coming on their own sake and Rabbi Shimon would
say they have to go down. The point is they're never coming
on their own sake, even if you don't bring them on the
same day as the קרבן. Korban, Because the הלכה is the wine
that goes with a קרבן, Korban if I'm supposed to bring it
on the same day but if I didn't I can bring it
a week later. So by saying that Rabbi Shimon would always say
they go down means that Rabbi Shimon would say that even if
they come on a separate day, at the end they're still not
coming on their own sake. They might be coming separately, but they're
not coming by virtue of themselves and therefore they're going to have
to go down. Okay. סלקא דעתך אמינא, Salka Da'atach Amina, הואיל ואמר
מר, Ho'il VeAmar Mar, מנחתם ונסכיהם בלילה, Minchatam VeNiskeyhem BaLailah, מנחתם ונסכיהם
למחר, Minchatam VeNiskeyhem LeMachar, that you can bring them even at night,
you know, after you've brought the קרבן or even on a separate
day, כנסכים הבאים בפני עצמן דמי, KeNesachim HaBaim Bifnei Atzman Dami, maybe
they're like קרבנות that come on their own accord, ומודה רבי שמעון
דלא ירדו, U'Modeh Rabbi Shimon DeLo Yerdu, and maybe he would say
they don't have to come down, קא משמע לן Ka Mashma Lan
that they do come down. Excellent. We will pick up with this
tomorrow. Enjoy.